Guide to the Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences Lecture Notes MC.391
New York University Archives
Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences Lecture Notes
1912-1984
New York University Archives
Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences
Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences. Library
MC.391
15.10 Linear Feet in 35 manuscript boxes
The Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences serves as New York Unviersity's mathematics research school. It grew from the Graduate School of Arts and Science's Department of Mathematics starting in 1935, when Richard Courant joined the faculty. The Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences Lecture Notes (1912-1984) mostly consists of lecture notes created by professors and teaching assistants from the Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences from the 1930s through the 1980s.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by Courant Institute Library, August 2023. The accession number associated with the transfer is 2023.058.
Arrangement
Arranged into three series:
Series I. Lecture Notes
Series II. Report and Remarks
Series III. Lectures at Other Institutions
All series are organized alphabetically by lecturer's name or title.
Historical Note
The Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences serves as New York Unviersity's mathematics research school. It grew from the Graduate School of Arts and Science's Department of Mathematics starting in 1935, when Richard Courant joined the faculty. The Institute was named the Institute for Mathematics and Mechanics in 1946. In that year and in 1954, research projects led to the establishment of the Division of Wave Propagation and Applied Mathematics and the Division of Magnetofluid Dynamics, respectively. NYU's first computer was installed at the Courant Institute in 1952, and its Computer Science program rapidly developed to include research on programming languages, computer graphics, parallel architectures, and theory. In 1965, the Institute was renamed after Richard Courant and moved to the newly constructed Warren Weaver Hall, where a majority of its activities still take place. The Division of Computational Fluid Dynamics was created in 1978.
Custodial History
It is assumed that these records were transferred to the Courant Institute Library by their creators. Documentation about these transfers varies across collections, and provenance is not always apparent. The transfer was treated as an administrative transfer to the New York University Archives from the Courant Institute in the summer of 2023 when the Courant Institute Library closed.
Content Description
The Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences Lecture Notes (1912-1984) contains lecture notes created by professors and teaching assistants from the Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences from the 1930s through the 1980s. Additionally, there is a report, a folder of joke "lecture notes" given to K.O. Friedrichs for his birthday, remarks delivered at Richard Courant's memorial, and lectures delivered by Richard Courant and others while teaching at different institutions. Notable lecturers include Richard Courant, Kurt O. Friedrichs, Fritz John, and Peter Lax, to name a few.
Mathematics -- Study and teaching -- United States; Applied mathematics.; Mathematicians; Research institutes.; Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences. Library; Courant, Richard, 1888-1972; Friedrichs, K. O. (Kurt Otto), 1901-1983
- Series I. Lecture Notes, 1935-1984; 13.56 Linear Feet in 31 manuscript boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of lectures delivered by professors and teaching assistants at the Courant Institute of Mathematical Science from 1935-1984. These lecture notes document the content and variety of classes at the Institute and the way in which professors taught over time. Course notes are labeled with the instructor's last name and the title of the class. Lectures cover such topics as Introduction to Mathematical Analysis, Theory of Functions of a Real Variable, and Mathematical Methods of Population Biology, among many others.
  - Artin, Emil, 1938-1954 (Box 1)
  - Bers, Lipman, 1951-1959 (Box 1, Box 2)
  - Bers, Lipman, et al., 1952 (Box 2)
  - Bohr, Harald, 1948 (Box 2)
  - Busemann, Herbert, 1938-1939 (Box 2)
  - Chern, S. S., 1965 (Box 2)
  - Courant, Richard, 1936-1953 (Box 2, Box 3, Box 4)
  - Courant, Richard with Appendix by Peter Lax, 1948 (Box 5)
  - Courant, Richard, et al., 1949-1950 (Box 5)
  - Courant, Richard and Kurt O. Friedrichs, 1943 (Box 6)
  - Courant, Richard, Kurt O. Friedrichs, and J. J., 1940-1946 (Box 6)
  - Davis, Constance, 1969-1972 (Box 6)
  - Davis, Martin, 1959-1977 (Box 6, Box 7)
  - Duistermaat, J. J., 1973 (Box 7)
  - Eckmann, B., 1947 (Box 7)
  - Eckweiler, Howard J., et al., 1946 (Box 7)
  - Eilenberg, S., 1948 (Box 7)
  - Flanders, 1939 (Box 7)
  - Friedman, Bernard, 1945-1957 (Box 7, Box 8)
  - Friedman, Bernard, et al., 1950 (Box 8)
  - Friedrichs, Kurt O., 1941-1973 (Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12, Box 13, Box 14)
  - Friedrichs, Kurt O., et al., 1957 (Box 15)
  - Fubini, G., 1941 (Box 15)
  - Glimm, James, 1965 (Box 15)
  - Grad, Harold, 1950-1954 (Box 15)
  - Greenberg, Philip J., 1973 (Box 15)
  - Grishman, R., 1976 (Box 15)
  - Grünbaum, F. Alberto, 1972 (Box 16)
  - Harrison, Malcolm C., 1970-1971 (Box 16)
  - Hilton, Peter, 1967-1968 (Box 16)
  - Hopf, Heinz, 1946-1963 (Box 16)
  - Hoppensteadt, F. C., 1977 (Box 17)
  - Hörmander, Lars, 1970 (Box 17)
  - Humphreys, J. E., 1971 (Box 17)
  - Isaacson, E., 1956-1957 (Box 17)
  - John, Fritz, 1946-1956 (Box 17, Box 18, Box 19)
  - Keller, H. B., circa 1968 (Box 19)
  - Keller, Joseph B., 1949-1950 (Box 19)
  - Keller, Joseph B. and Stuart Antman, 1968 (Box 19)
  - Kline, circa 1939-1940 (Box 19)
  - Lax, Anneli, 1965 (Box 19)
  - Lax, Peter D., 1950-1963 (Box 20)
  - Lax, Peter D., Samuel Z. Burstein, and Anneli Lax, 1972 (Box 20)
  - Lewis, Robert M. and Joseph B. Keller, 1963 (Box 20)
  - Lubkin, Samuel, 1956 (Box 21)
  - Manacher, Glenn K., 1971 (Box 21)
  - Mullish, Henry, 1971 (Box 21)
  - Mullish, Henry and Max Goldstein, 1973 (Box 21)
  - Neumann, B. H., 1961-1962 (Box 21)
  - Nirenberg, Louis, 1948-1974 (Box 21, Box 22)
  - Percus, J. K., 1967-1984 (Box 22)
  - Peskin, Charles S., 1975-1976 (Box 22)
  - Peters, Arthur, 1948 (Box 22)
  - Problem Seminar, Mathematics 302, 1950 (Box 23)
  - Rademacher, Hans, 1949-1951 (Box 23)
  - Rellich, Franz, 1950-1953 (Box 23)
  - Richtmyer, R. D., 1961-1964 (Box 23)
  - Robbins, H., 1940-1941 (Box 24)
  - Schwartz, Jack, 1957-1961 (Box 24)
  - Schwartz, Jacob T., 1959-1975 (Box 24, Box 25)
  - Schwartz, Jacob T. and Melvin Hausner, 1964 (Box 26)
  - Schwartz, Laurent, 1964 (Box 26)
  - Shapiro, Harold N., 1948-1952 (Box 26, Box 27)
  - Shapiro, H. S., 1961-1962 (Box 27)
  - Shaw, Philip, 1978 (Box 27, Box 28)
  - Shephard, R., 1947-1948 (Box 28)
  - Shiffman, M., circa 1946-1955 (Box 28)
  - Siegel, Carl L., 1945-1948 (Box 28, Box 29)
  - Singer, 1975 (Box 29)
  - Stoker, J. J., 1939-1964 (Box 29)
  - Stone, M. H., circa 1969 (Box 30)
  - Takeuchi, circa 1976 (Box 30)
  - Tamarkin, J. D. and Willy Feller, 1941 (Box 30)
  - Ungar, Peter, 1959 (Box 30)
  - Varadarajan, V. S., 1961-1962 (Box 30)
  - Varadhan, S. R. S., 1967-1974 (Box 30, Box 31)
  - Veblen, Oswald and John von Neumann, 1935-1936 (Box 31)
  - Venkataratyudu, T., 1953 (Box 31)
  - Wang, Chi-teh, 1948 (Box 31)
  - Weber, E., 1941 (Box 31)
  - Whitehead, Earl Glen, Jr., 1971-1972 (Box 31)
- Series II. Report and Remarks, 1968-1972; 0.88 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes
  This series reflects additional responsibilities of the professors and instructors at the Courant Institute, including providing reports to committees, such as the report from the Magneto-Fluid Dynamics Division to the Standing Committee, and remarks at events like the memorial service for Richard Courant and the birthday celebration for K. O. Friedrichs.
  - Magneto-Fluid Dynamics Division Report, 1968 (Box 32)
  - "Richard Courant, 1888-1972: Remarks Delivered at the Memorial" (Box 32)
  - "To K. O. Friedrichs on His Seventieth Birthday", undated (Box 32)
- Series III. Lectures at Other Institutions, 1912-1965; 1.54 Linear Feet in 4 manuscript boxes
  This series consists of lectures delivered by Courant professors and instructors at other institutions, the majority of which were given by Richard Courant at the University of Göttingen.
  - Courant, Richard -- Princeton University, 1932 (Box 32)
  - Courant, Richard -- University of Göttingen, 1912-1932 (Box 32, Box 33, Box 34)
  - David, Martin -- Yeshiva University, 1960-1961 (Box 35)
  - Varadarajan, V. S. -- Indian Statistical Institute, 1964-1965 (Box 35)